Guide to the Rendez-vous Hautes Montagnes: files and journal, 1968-1994
Department of Special Collections
Rendez-vous Hautes Montagnes: files and journal,
1968-1994
M1234
Beardsley, Irene A., collector.
.5 linear ft. (1 manuscript box)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Correspondence, organizational files, and the journal, 1969-1984. Includes Beardsley's research notes and typescript about the history of American women's mountaineering, ca. 1970, that was to have been used in von Reznicek's 2nd edition of VON DER KRINOLINE ZUM 6 GRAD, but which was not printed.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Irene A. Beardsley, 2001.
Historical Note
Organization formed in Engelberg, Switzerland, by Felicitas von Reznicek in 1968 to encourage women's climbing. Irene Beardsley was the American delegate. The group organized international climbs and an annual meeting, and through their biannual publication, "Rendez-vous-Journal," facilitated contacts between women mountaineers and reported significant climbs and expeditions.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Correspondence, organizational files, and the journal, 1969-1984. Includes Beardsley's research notes and typescript about the history of American women's mountaineering, ca. 1970, that was to have been used in von Reznicek's 2nd edition of VON DER KRINOLINE ZUM 6 GRAD, but which was not printed.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Armstrong, Patricia K.; Atwood, Stephanie.; Bartley, Ann.; Beardsley, Irene A.; Blum, Arlene, 1945-; Bunin Yokell, Jane.; Frost, Dorene.; Huisman, Cate.; Isherwood, Dana Smith.; Jensen, Joan V.; Johnson, Beverly.; Knowlton, Elizabeth.; Komarkova, Vera.; Lilley, Barbara.; Liska, Carol. A.; Melchior, Siri.; Mendenhall, Ruth Dyar.; Miller, Irene B.; Mullen, Frances.; Nickerson, Donna.; Petrilak, Stephanie I.; Reid, Christine L.; Reznicek, Felicitas von, 1904-; Sweet, Meriby.; Watson, Vera.; Young, Margaret.; Rendez-vous Hautes Montagnes.; Mountaineering--History.; Mountaineering expeditions.; Women mountaineers--United States--History.
Collection Contents
- RHM - United States Members1974 - 1980 (Folder 1)
  Membership lists of US members of RHM from 1974 to 1980. Climbing resumes of some members.
- RHM - History Notes (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes made on the history of women's climbing in the United States by Irene Ortenburger.
  Irene B. Ortenburger
- RHM - Correspondence of Felicitas von Reznicek1969 May 7 - 1980 Dec. 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Letters from Felicitas von Reznicek, president of RHM, to Irene Ortenburger, US delegate, concerning the organization of the US members of RHM, the summer meets in Europe, and the gathering of information on the history of American women's climbing for a chapter in a new edition of "Von der Krinoline zum Sechsten Grad," by von Reznicek.
  Irene B. Ortenburger; Felicitas von Reznicek
- RHM - Correspondence with Members1970 Mar. 29 - 1978 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Letters from Irene Ortenburger to US members of RHM, information on summer meets, some letters from US members reporting on climbing activites.
  Mireille Marks; Irene B. Ortenburger; Felicitas von Reznicek
- RHM - Journals1968 - 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Most of the annual Rendez-vous Journals from 1968 to 1983.
- RHM - Correspondence I1969 Oct. 5 - 1970 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Miscellaneous correspondence to Irene Ortenburger from US members of RHM and others gathering information for the history of American women's climbing.
  Deirdre G. Byers; Jack C. Dozier; Norman G. Dyhrenfurth; John Ebert; Dorothy Harrington; Raymond W. Jewell, Jr.; James P. McCarthy; Felicitas von Reznicek; Sally Richards; Howard Stansbury; Bradford B. VanDiver; Dorothy K. Walker; American Alpine Club; Potomac Appalachian Trail Club; Chicago Mountaineering Club; Colorado Mountain Club; Iowa Mountaineers; The Mountaineers; Mazamas
- RHM - Correspondence II1970 July 22 - 1975 Mar. 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Correspondence to Irene Ortenburger, mostly from US members of RHM. Brochure for the meeting of RHM in the Pyrenees in 1975, with extensive guide to the climbs.
  William Kemsley; Mireille Marks; Felicitas von Reznicek; Ray Smutek; BackPack; Off Belay
- RHM - Correspondence III1975 Oct. - 1992 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Correspondence to Irene Ortenburger, mostly from US members of RHM. List of delegates (country representatives) from approximately 1978. Incomplete list of all members. Programs and announcements from some meetings from 1979 to 1992. Stephanie Petrilak takes over as US representative in 1980. Nadia Le Bon takes over in 1989.
  Nadia Billia Le Bon; Susi Muller; Felicitas von Reznicek
- RHM - AAC Clippings1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Copies of entries in the American Alpine Club Annals and the American Alpine Journal about early American women climbers. Other typed notes taken by Irene Ortenburger for the proposed chapter in a new edition of the book " Von der Krinoline zum Sechsten Grad, " by Felicitas von Reznicek.
  Irene Ayres; Eleanor E. Bartlett; Gertrude Bell; Meta Claudia Brevoort; Helen Buck; Marguerite Schnellbacher Coveny; Elizabeth S. Cowles; Georgia Engelhard Cromwell; Eleanor Davis Ehrman; Marjory Bridge Farquhar; Geraldine FitzGerald; Larie Renshaw Frazeur; Edwina Fay Fuller; Kate Gardiner; Lillian Gest; Dora Keen Handy; Marjorie Hurd; Elizabeth Knowlton; Elizabeth Larned MacCarthy; Lulie Nettleton; Miriam O'Brian; Marion Randall Parsons; Elizabeth C. Partridge; Annie Smith Peck; Polly Prescott; Christine L. Reid; Miriam Underhill; Elizabeth D. Woolsey; Fanny Bullock Workman
- RHM - Manuscript1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Two copies of the manuscript by Irene Ortenburger for the proposed chapter in a new edition of the book " Von der Krinoline zum Sechsten Grad, " by Felicitas von Reznicek. Second copy has corrections by unknown person. The second edition was never published.